#### Contact

8618064285 (Mobile)

www.linkedin.com/in/ vishwanathjha1 (LinkedIn) vishwanathjha.blogspot.in/ (Blog)

# Top Skills

Data Mining Analytics SQL

# Languages

Hindi (Native or Bilingual)

Maithili (Native or Bilingual)

English (Native or Bilingual)

### Certifications

Foundations of Data Analysis
KlexploRx, Explore Statistics with R
Learning From Data (Introductory
Machine Learning course)
AMCAT Certified Business Analyst

PH525.1x Statistics and R for the Life Sciences

# Vishwa Nath Jha

Founder, CEO at Saarthi.ai | Augmenting Contact Centres with Multilingual Call Centre Al Agents

Bengaluru

# Summary

Vishwa Nath Jha is a serial entrepreneur, AI thought leader, researcher, founder & CEO of Saarthi.ai - an omni channel multilingual conversational AI enterprise platform. He's on a mission to realise his dream of complete digital inclusion in India. His primary research areas revolves around dialogue agents & speech technologies in low resource languages. He's part of multiple government & industry committees which are responsible for designing policies and frameworks to spur the research ecosystem pertaining to Indian languages.

# Past Keynote Engagements:

- 1. World Al Show, Mauritius
- 2. NITI Ayog
- 3. Ministry of Electronics & Information Technology
- 4. FICCI Indian Language Internet Alliance
- 5. NASSCOM
- 6. IEEE DeepTech.Ai NLP technical Symposium
- 7. SBICAP Securities Al conference
- 8. Bhashantara 2019
- 9. PvData Pune Jan 2020
- 10. d(ai)logue Affine Analytics Feb, 2020
- 11. Voice Tech India

#### Areas of Interest:

Natural Language Processing, Deep Learning, Speech Recognition, Conversational AI, Goal Oriented Dialogue Systems, Reinforcement Learning, Startups

# Experience

Saarthi.ai Founder, CEO June 2017 - Present (3 years 3 months) Bengaluru Area, India

Gamut Analytics
Founder, CEO
September 2016 - Present (4 years)
Bengaluru Area, India

### Simplilearn

Adjunct Faculty of Machine Learning & Deep Learning February 2018 - November 2018 (10 months)
Bengaluru Area, India

During weekends I conduct hands-on virtual bootcamp on Machine Learning & Deep Learning with Python programming.

GamutData Consulting
Founder, CEO
August 2015 - January 2017 (1 year 6 months)
Mumbai Area, India

As a Data Science Evangelist, I helped thousands of students, faculties & professionals to grow into Artificial Intelligence and Data Science practitioners via my bootcamps on Machine Learning, Natural Language Processing, Deep learning, Big Data, Python, R, Apache Spark, Tableau, etc.

I collaborated with multiple data driven organizations such as: Fractal Analytics, Synechron, Edelweiss, GlobalEdge, etc. as well as with EdTech startups such as: Upgrad, Zeolearn, Ufaber ,etc.

I also worked with students at IIM Ranchi, MISB Bocconi and professors at University of Houston, Texas, etc. to propagate Data Science & Artificial Intelligence.

#### Germin8

Software Engineer - Algorithms March 2015 - August 2015 (6 months)

Created an application to predict the sentiment of tweets, Facebook posts & comments. Applied appropriate pre-processing steps to clean the data and wrote scripts to extract 60+ features. Slang replacement and making

sense of hash tags were key challenges which were taken care of. Fitted and tuned One – Vs - Rest SVM classifiers to classify the documents into positive, neutral and negative. Later fitted an ensemble chain of classifiers to improve the accuracy of the classifiers. Used R, Python & Java for successfully implementing the algorithms.

#### IntelligenceNODE

**Data Scientist** 

October 2014 - February 2015 (5 months)

Developed algorithms of a data product for E - commerce clients largely catering to problems like pricing & classification of products. It involved web crawling to extract details about millions of products listed on different websites, data cleaning, extracting 70+ features, building and tuning predictive model to predict the categories each product belonged to.

Set up the Big Data infrastructure to scale the operation as the size of data ran into hundreds of Terabytes

"Python" was used for crawling and "R" was used to clean data, extract features, building models & tuning.

# Fractal Analytics

Analyst

January 2014 - October 2014 (10 months)

Role: Team Member

Team Name: Business Pulse

Team Size: 5

Client: One of the world's largest CPG giant

Description:

In the beginning of each month, the team creates a shipment glide path using a Log Linear regression model customized for each region. This glidepath acts as the basis for a daily shipment plan which is leveraged by the execution teams. The 2 Key inputs to build an accurate glidepath are:

- 1. Historical shipment data
- 2. Knowledge of regional market dynamics

Additionally, based on actual daily shipment information this glide path model also provides the likely hood of achieving a monthly target and the potential gap in cases where company is over shipping or under shipping.

Role: Team Member

Team Name: Digital Solutions

Team Size: 10

Client: One of the world's largest CPG giant

Description:

Work closely with clients to create solutions to their e-commerce related business problems by :

- 1. Identifying and pitching new business opportunities for the client
- 2. Create high impact IP's for clients to measure and enhance their market presence
- 3. Exploring whitespaces and working to convert them into business engagements

Mu Sigma
Trainee Decision Scientist
June 2013 - December 2013 (7 months)

Bangalore, India

Role: Team Lead

Team Name: International Demand Migration

Team Size: 4

Client: One of the world's largest search engine

Description:

Help them make better decisions by

- 1. Processing big data into condensed & consumable reports
- 2. Generating actionable business insights
- 3. Suggesting new techniques to enhance already existing ideology
- 4. Liaisoning between the client and the delivery team for all the adhoc requests and ongoing projects
- 5. Engaging with the client to understand business dynamics and identify questions that can be addressed through analytics
- 6. Managing operational workflow and ensure seamless delivery for both quick turnaround analysis and long term projects
- 7. Identifying and harvesting new business opportunities at the client side by preparing business plans

# Education

Dayananda Sagar College Of Engineering
Bachelor's Degree, Information Science & Engineering · (2009 - 2013)

Kendriya Vidyalaya Masjid Moth
AISSCE, Science with Information Practices & Mathematics · (2006 - 2008)

Holy Mission High School AISSE · (2002 - 2006)